OK, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ח Kaf-Chet Bava
Metzia 28, although we're a bit behind, and we pick up at
the bottom of כ"ז עמוד א', Kaf-Zayin amud aleph, and our learning
should be in the תפילה tefilla for the merit for the protection
of our חיילים וחיילות hayalim ve-hayalot and the speedy return of the
hostages and a speedy end to the war. OK, so we are
picking up at the bottom of כ"ז עמוד א' Kaf-Zayin amud aleph
and we're dealing, the משנה Mishna spoke about how from the פסוק,
pasuk, the mention of the word שמלה, simla, garment, we learn the
idea of סימנים simanim and טועים to'im that that you return an
אבידה aveida if there are people that are demanding it and if
there is some type of a mark, a distinguishing mark, a סימן,
siman, and it led to the גמרא Gemara to a whole discussion
about exactly what we learn from all the different words in the
פסוקים: pesukim: שה, seh, אבידה, aveida, שמלה, simla, and so on. And
the most recent part of that discussion was a question about whether
where you learn the idea that something has to be worth a
פרוטה, pruta, if it's less than a פרוטה pruta you have no
obligation to return it, do you learn it from the word of
תאבד tovad ממנו, mimenu, lost, something that is considered significant that it
was lost, or מצאתה, metzata, something that is significant that it was
found? And so yesterday's דף daf dealt with some of the back
and forth about where exactly you're learning it out from and there's
no real נפקא מינא, nafka mina, it's just a question about which
part of the verse you emphasize. But now we're going to pick
up here at the bottom of כ"ז עמוד א' Kaf-Zayin amud aleph
to say that there may actually be a difference הלכתית halachically between
which verse you learn it from. OK, so we pick up from
the
following,
רבא אמר. Rava amar. So it's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6
lines down in the medium-sized lines, beginning of the line, near the
beginning. רבא אמר פרוטה שהוזלה איכא בינייהו. Rava amar pruta she-huzla ika
beinayhu. No, no, no, it makes a difference which part of the
verse you learn it from. If something was lost and it was
worth a פרוטה pruta and now it's worth less than a פרוטה,
pruta, 'cause do you emphasize when it's lost it has to be
significant or when it's found it has to be significant? OK, so
that's a very reasonable way of explaining the debate. OK,
איכא בינייהו. ika beinayhu. מאן דאמר מאשר תאבד, man de-amar me-asher tovad,
that something that's lost from you, so איכא ika then, when it
was lost it was worth a פרוטה. pruta. מאן דאמר ומצאתה, man
de-amar u-metzata, from when it was found, ליכא, leika, then now that
it's found it's not worth a פרוטה. pruta. So how does the
person finding it know exactly? But let's say it was nothing happened
to the object, just the market value went down. It was an
apple, and when it was lost an apple was worth a פרוטה,
pruta, and now when the guy finds it, he doesn't know exactly
when it was lost, but now he does know that apples are
not worth a פרוטה, pruta, or maybe he does know that when
it was lost, he could tell it was lost yesterday, whatever the
case might be. OK, and so do you go by when it
was lost or when it was found? So that seems like very
reasonable, and then the reverse could be if it was worth less
than a פרוטה pruta and then now worth more. But the גמרא
Gemara doesn't like this. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
OK, so it says, מאן דאמר מאשר תאבד איכא מאן דאמר ומצאתה
ליכא. man de-amar me-asher tovad ika man de-amar u-metzata leika. ולמאן דאמר
אשר תאבד, u-le-man de-amar asher tovad, so the גמרא Gemara says, no
wait one minute, even if you're focusing on the פסוק pasuk that
says lost from you, הא בעינן ומצאתה, ha ba'inan u-metzata, you can't
deny that the פסוק pasuk also says and it's found, so it's
a funny point of the גמרא. Gemara. Somehow you obviously would look
at both words even if your עיקר דרשה ikker drasha is from
one of them. So clearly it would have to be worth a
פרוטה pruta when it was found as well, וליכא, u-leika, and you
wouldn't have that in this case. אלא, ela, says the גמרא, Gemara,
fine, the reverse. פרוטה שהוקרה איכא בינייהו, pruta she-hokra ika beinayhu, when
it was lost it was less than a פרוטה pruta and now
it's worth a פרוטה. pruta. מאן דאמר ומצאתה, man de-amar u-metzata,
who emphasized when it's being found, איכא, ika, then when it was
found it was worth a פרוטה. pruta. ומאן דאמר אשר תאבד ליכא,
u-man de-amar asher tovad leika, but if you emphasize when it was
lost, when it was lost it wasn't worth a פרוטה. pruta. Alright,
now the גמרא Gemara is going to say the same thing. ולמאן
דאמר ומצאתה איכא, u-le-man de-amar u-metzata ika, even if you emphasize the
פסוק pasuk from when it was found, הא בעינן אשר תאבד וליכא,
ha ba'inan asher tovad u-leika, don't you also need to satisfy the
פסוק pasuk when it was lost? So again, a strange גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says, no, אשר תאבד asher tovad is teaching you
something else, ומצאתה u-metzata is teaching you something else, but the גמרא
Gemara somehow feels like if there's an idea of a פרוטה, pruta,
you can't, you would obviously have to look at both words even
if you put your emphasis on one of them. So it can't
be the נפקא מינא nafka mina is when it was worth less
and now more or more and now less. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלא, ela, fine, here's the נפקא מינא. nafka mina. פרוטה שהוקרה
והוזלה וחזרה והוקרה איכא בינייהו. pruta she-hokra ve-huzla ve-hazara ve-hokra ika beinayhu.
It was worth a פרוטה pruta and then it became less than
a פרוטה pruta in the interim and now it's back up to
a פרוטה. pruta. And somehow the person who finds it knows about
all of this. מאן דאמר אשר תאבד איכא. man de-amar asher tovad
ika.
If you say that it was lost or put your emphasis on
when it was lost, so when it was lost it was worth
a פרוטה. pruta. Then there's a secondary requirement that it also has
to be worth a פרוטה pruta when it was found, but the
emphasis is when it was lost. So OK, at that moment it's
a פרוטה pruta and because in the end when it was found
it was also a פרוטה, pruta, you check that box as well
and there's a מצוה mitzvah to return it. ומאן דאמר ומצאתה, u-man
de-amar u-metzata, but if you focus on when it was found, that's
the end of the process, so the גמרא Gemara is going to
say that doesn't mean just the end, if you start with your
emphasis on when it was found, it really means the entire process.
בעינן דאית ביה שיעור מציאה משעת אבידה ועד שעת מציאה, be’inan de’it
bei shiur metzia mi’shas aveidah v’ad she’as metzia, you would need that
it would be something worth finding from the entire process. So not
exactly clear to me why, a, the גמרא Gemara assumes that you
would have to include the other verse, the other word, and the
other end point. And b, even if you are, that somehow why
when you emphasize the beginning it's okay if it fluctuates in the
middle, whereas if you emphasize it at the end it has to
be minimum value throughout. But anyway, that's the way רבא Rava at
least explains there could be some difference based on which part of
the פסוק Pasuk you learn it from. Okay, now we get onto
a new topic, very last line of כ"ז עמוד א'. Chof Zayin
Amud Aleph. איבעיא להו: Iba'yehu: the question was raised: סימנים דאורייתא או
דרבנן? simanim d’Oraisa o d’Rabbanan? This has been referenced before in the
גמרא. Gemara. Is the idea that you return it with
סימנים—and simanim again, there are like three levels of סימנים; simanim; we
will see. There's something that's not even a סימן, siman, you know,
it was a black umbrella, שכיח, shach, you know,
you've just described 90% of the umbrellas. Okay, then there's something that's
a סימן, siman, but you know, it narrows it down, but it
doesn't make it like oh, only the owner would know
this. You know, it was a blue umbrella, it was a Mets
umbrella. Okay, a lot of Mets umbrellas in New York, you know,
but okay, but it certainly it's much more likely than not that
you're the owner. That's a normal סימן. siman. And then you have
the first one isn't really a סימן siman at all, then you
have a normal סימן, siman, and then you have a סימן מובהק,
siman muvhak, something that really only the owner would know. You know,
the third
prong is broken in the umbrella and it's a Mets umbrella or
something like that. Okay, so when we're talking about סימנים דאורייתא, simanim
d’Oraisa, we're talking about the middle category. A סימן מובהק, siman muvhak,
you know, it's got a tear here and this that, everybody agrees
that that works. The question is whether the תורה Torah would have
allowed you to assume ownership and to identify it and to return
it on the basis of an average סימן. siman. That's the question.
Okay, איבעיא להו: Iba'yehu: סימנים דאורייתא או דרבנן? simanim d’Oraisa o d’Rabbanan?
Is it דאורייתא d’Oraisa or דרבנן? d’Rabbanan? מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka
mina? What's the difference? Because obviously either way, we know the principle
is you return an אבידה aveida if there's a סימן. siman. So
now top of כ"ז עמוד ב', Chof Zayin Amud Beis, so the
גמרא Gemara says: להדורי גט אשה בסימנים. l’hadurei get isha b’simanim. No,
the difference is that when you rely on it not just for
a question of ממונות, mamonus, of property ownership, and חז"ל Chazal have
a lot of latitude when it comes to property ownership, you know,
they can sort of assign who owns something and who doesn't own
something. But the question is: would you trust it in order to
return a גט get to a woman? She could give a סימן
siman and you therefore know she had to have received it and
you assume she received it, you gave it to her, now you're
going to let her remarry. So
if it's דאורייתא, d’Oraisa, okay, דאורייתא d’Oraisa that proves ownership and it
would work even in a category of personal status and איסור והיתר.
issur v’heter. But if it was only the Rabbis have allowed it
to work, that's something they can play around with when it's a
question of monetary ownership, not when they're going to actually permit somebody
to be understood to be a divorced woman if the דאורייתא d’Oraisa
הלכה halacha would not recognize her as such, would not feel that
there was sufficient evidence for that. So that's the נפקא מינה: nafka
mina: להדורי גט אשה בסימנים. l’hadurei get isha b’simanim. אי אמרת דאורייתא,
ei amart d’Oraisa, if it's a דאורייתא d’Oraisa principle that you can
assume ownership, that the תורה Torah recognizes, you know, good evidence of
ownership based on סימנים, simanim, מהדרינן, mahadrinan, you would return it. ואי
אמרת דרבנן, v’ei amart d’Rabbanan, but if it was only rabbinic, no,
כי עבדי רבנן תקנתא בממונא, ki avdi Rabbanan takanta b’mamona, they might
have been able to sort of set the rules when it comes
to monetary ownership, okay, that's not directly changing any personal status and
איסור והיתר, issur v’heter, and you know, the גמרא Gemara learns that
elsewhere: הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beis din hefker, and חז"ל Chazal
have the ability to assign ownership. That could work בממונא, b’mamona, they
could do it in monetary, אבל באיסורא לא עבדי רבנן תקנתא, aval
b’issura lo avdi Rabbanan takanta, but they wouldn't have the power to
assume that a woman was divorced if the תורה Torah would not
recognize that, again maybe there's some cases we do, but as a
general rule we would not assume that they would have an ability
to change evidence in what would be considered that she would be
divorced. So is it, does it work דאורייתא d’Oraisa or not? תא
שמע, ta shma, come in here. So we're going to quote our
משנה: Mishnah: אף השמלה היתה בכלל כל אלה. af hasimla haysa bechlal
kol eileh. You know, the משנה Mishnah says that the garment mentioned
in the פסוק Pasuk would have been included in, you know, על
שור על שה, al shor al seh, you know, על כל אבידה,
al kol aveida, and שמלה simla was mentioned to tell you the
principle of סימנים, simanim, that you return it based on סימנים. simanim.
So the גמרא Gemara says, excuse me, so still quoting the משנה:
Mishnah: ולמה יצאה, v’lama yatsa, why was שמלה simla singled out in
the פסוק? Pasuk? להקיש אליה לומר לך מה שמלה מיוחדת שיש בה
סימנים ויש לה תובעים. l’hakiys eleha lomar lach mah simla meyushedes she’yesh
lah simanim v’yesh lah tovin. So the same way שמלה simla is
something that, a, is distinct, that a normal garment has some type
of a סימן, siman, a distinguishing mark, and also people are demanding
it, meaning there's no יאוש ye’ush and the owners are still demanding
it, so אף
כל דבר, af kol davar, that teaches the principle that anything שיש
לו סימנים ויש לו תובעים חייב להכריז, she’yesh lo simanim v’yesh lo
tovin chayav l’hachriz, that's the type of thing that you הכריז achriz
on and you have to return. So bottom line is that the
משנה Mishnah says that we learn from the word of שמלה simla
the principle of סימנים, simanim, that's what it's teaching me in the
תורה. Torah. So clearly that seems to be that סימנים simanim are
דאורייתא, d’Oraisa, that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא. d’Oraisa. So clearly that seems
to be that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Very simple פשט pshat
of the משנה. Mishnah. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
תנא תובעין איצטריכא ליה סימנים כדי נסבה. tana tov'in itztericha lei simanim
kedi nasvah. But no, you know, the real לימוד limud from the
פסוק pasuk is that there has to be still people that demand
it. There can't have been יאוש. ye'ush. The idea that it throws
in you return something with סימנים, simanim, that's an אסמכתא, asmachta, that's
only Rabbinic, we're hinging it on the פסוק, pasuk, but really from
the תורה Torah you would have really needed there to be witnesses
to say we can identify this object as belonging to ראובן. Reuven.
So even though the משנה Mishnah mentions סימנים, simanim, that's being thrown
in, that's not what the תורה Torah is really telling you. The
תורה Torah is really would require עדים edim and סימנים simanim is
telling you the idea that there was not yet יאוש. ye'ush. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, ta shema,
let's keep on going. חמור בסימני אוכף, chamor besimanei ukaf,
we have the ברייתא braisa that we quoted yesterday that says that
you come that you return a donkey by being able to give
the identifying marks, the סימנים simanim on the saddle.
So you see again and that's saying that that's what you learn
from the word חמור chamor in the תורה, Torah, that it's teaching
you return it based on סימנים. simanim. Again, clearly from the פסוקים
psukim we're learning the idea of סימנים. simanim. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, also there it's not really literal. אימא בעדי אוכף. eima
be'adei ukaf.
No, practically we return it סימנים, simanim, that's the Rabbinic layer, but
what the תורה Torah is telling you will claim is that you
return it when there's witnesses that testify that they recognize it, that
סימנים simanim would actually not be good. It would have said in
the משנה, Mishnah, but that's not how it should be understood. Really
understood based on עדים. edim. אימא בעדי אוכף. eima be'adei ukaf. תא
שמע, ta shema,
let's try again. והיה עמך עד דרוש אחיך אותו, vehaya imcha ad
derosh achicha oso, again another דרשה drasha from the פסוק, pasuk, it'll
be with you until your friend comes to seek it out. So
the ברייתא braisa says, וכי תעלה על דעתך שיתננו לו קודם שידרשנו?
vechi ta'ala al da'atacha sheyittenennu lo kodem sheyidrashennu? What does the פסוק
pasuk mean until he seeks it out? You think you would just
go give it to somebody without them asking? Now of course if
you knew who it was, you would have to give it to
them. But in a case where you didn't know whose it was,
of course there's no going to be giving back until somebody you
know sort of comes to claim it. So what's the פסוק pasuk
coming to teach you? אלא, ela, what it's teaching you, the ברייתא
braisa says is דרשהו אם רמאי הוא או אינו רמאי. darshehu im
ramai hu o eino ramai. So you have to make sure that
he's not being deceitful. That even just because somebody says they claimed
it, you have to demand some type of evidence to know that
he really is telling the truth and he really is the person
that lost it. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו, mai lav,
is that ברייתא braisa not coming to tell you the principle of
בסימנים? besimanim? That you determine whether they're telling the truth based on
whether they can identify it with סימנים? simanim? So that already is
a very weak proof, it doesn't say סימנים, simanim, it just says
you have to you know give some evidence. So here there's an
easy answer. לא בעדים. lo be'edim. No, maybe it means you give
evidence by bringing witnesses to testify that it's yours. But again, there's
certainly that ברייתא braisa doesn't mention סימנים simanim at all. תא שמע,
ta shema, let's come in here, let's try again. אין מעידין אלא
על פרצוף פנים עם החוטם. ein me'idin ela al partzuf panim im
hachotem. So that now we're going so now the first set of
proofs were about אבידה, aveidah, but the ברייתא braisa or משנה Mishnah
that seemed to link it to a פסוק pasuk and that proves
it's דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Okay, that's the question of the source. Now we're
going to try it based on the actual law because you said
that the נפקא מינה nafka mina was can you allow a woman
to remarry based on סימנים? simanim? That would prove that סימנים simanim
are דאורייתא. de'oraisa. So now we're going to show you sometimes we
let a woman remarry based on סימנים. simanim. Okay, so what does
it say? It says that you do not testify that if somebody
says, you know witnesses say they saw this woman's husband dead, how
do they know it was the husband? So אין מעידין אלא על
פרצוף פנים עם החוטם. ein me'idin ela al partzuf panim im hachotem.
They would have to say we actually saw the face together with
the nose, that we really saw enough of the face that we
could definitely identify it as the husband. That would be required to
testify that he died to let the woman remarry. אף על פי
שיש סימנים בגופו ובכליו, af al pi sheyesh simanim begufo ubechelav,
even though there are distinguishing marks on his body and on his
clothes, that's not enough. So here the ברייתא braisa seems to be
very clear that when it comes to a personal status issue, an
איסור issur issue, you need direct recognition and it is not enough
to say oh yes, we know he had a birthmark. Oh yes,
those were the clothes, we knew those were his clothes. So it
seems that סימנים simanim does not suffice. So let's see how the
גמרא Gemara answers that, and this is a real halakhic principle, halakhic
law. It's not just a question of the source. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, שמע מינה, shma mina, can we see from
there סימנים לאו דאורייתא, simanim lav de'oraisa, that סימנים simanim do not
have דאורייתא de'oraisa weight? So no, אמרי גופו דארוך וגוץ. amri gufo
de'aroch vegootz. No, it means that they're not really distinguishing marks. You
know, it says, oh he was short, he was tall, things that
were, yeah, six feet, I remember that his her husband was six
feet tall. So that's the weakest category of סימנים. simanim. It is
some descriptive remark, but it is nothing that really gives us any
confidence to think that you really got the person right. Okay, and
that's what it means that you can't testify. Now that's a little
weak because it says you have to recognize the face. So if
there were סימנים simanim that would be good without recognizing the face,
you know, more specific סימנים, simanim, you would think that it would
say that those would also be good. By emphasizing that the face
is what is needed and סימנים simanim are not good, seems to
be saying that all סימנים simanim are not good unless there's direct
recognition of the face, but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is trying to
get out of this by saying no, no, no, it just means
weak סימנים simanim are not sufficient. Okay, so סימנים simanim is what?
Again,
דארוך וגוטי, dearoch veguti, either he's tall or he's short, כליו keilav
and what his clothes were, דחיישינן לשאלה, dechashinan lisheilah,
that even if you say that we recognize, yes, we can tell
that those are ראובן's Reuven clothes, we know what they look like,
nevertheless, how do you know he was wearing his clothes? There have
been cases in the past where misidentification, somebody was carrying somebody else's
wallet, you know, so there, there it is not good enough to
give us that confidence. So could be that סימנים דאורייתא, simanim deoraisa,
but that's saying, you know, that those are not strong enough סימנים.
simanim. But a strong סימן siman maybe would be good דאורייתא. deoraisa.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אי חיישינן
לשאלה, ei chashinan lisheilah, if we're worried that somebody might be borrowing
somebody else's clothes or garments or so on, because right, that case
is one where actually you say we really did recognize the clothes,
but you're saying it doesn't satisfy the סימן, siman, you know, even
the middle category of a reasonable סימן siman because maybe somebody is,
you know, maybe he lent out his clothes and somebody else was
borrowing his clothes. Is that really enough, the גמרא's Gemara going to
say, to get something out of this reasonable middle category of סימן?
siman? You're saying it is. Let's test that theory. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, אי חיישינן לשאלה, ei chashinan lisheilah, if we're concerned
about lending, חמור בסימני אוכף היכי מהדרינן? chamor besimanei ukaf heichi mahadrinan?
Why do you return a donkey when you can testify to or
you know you can you can give סימנים simanim to what the
saddle looked like? Maybe the saddle belongs to the owner, but maybe
it's lent out to a different donkey. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אמרי אוכף לא שאלי אינשי, amri ukaf lo sha'ali inshi, אוכפה,
uchfa,
when it comes to a saddle, people don't lend out their saddles.
Why? משום דמיכאב, mishum demiskav, it causes like irritation on the donkey,
you know, it's broken in and it's appropriate for the particular donkey,
ליה לחמרא, lei lachamra, you know, it'll it'll cause irritation for the
donkey. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, okay, so that's so that's so that's
the answer. We don't rely on testifying to the clothes because by
clothes we assume people might lend out their clothes, even if סימנים
דאורייתא, simanim deoraisa, but that would be a question we would have.
But it would not always apply. There would be certain types of
clothes or saddles or whatever, certain types of things people would not
lend out. But as a general rule, סימנים simanim would be דאורייתא,
deoraisa, but sometimes we do have to worry that you lent these
things out. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara will go continues
with it. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, if you want I could say
the following: כליו, keilav, the reason that you don't trust the clothes
is maybe we don't assume people lent out their clothes and if
you could definitely identify it as ראובן's Reuven clothes, you could testify
that it was ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven died. But maybe the
סימנים simanim of the clothes are the very generic type like the
סימנים simanim of the body. So כליו keilav is what? בחיורי ובסומקי,
bechivrei uvesumkei, yeah, it was white clothes, red clothes. It was very
generic. Black umbrella, white umbrella, not a good enough identifier. Okay, and
that's why you cannot rely on it.
Okay, so now what have we said? We have said that we
tried to bring proof that סימנים דאורייתא simanim deoraisa because it seems
to be that we're learning it from פסוקים pesukim by אבידה, aveidah,
but we could say, you know, that's really not what we're learning
from the פסוקים. pesukim. From the פסוקים pesukim we're really learning the
idea of עדים. eidim. Then we tried to say it looks like
סימנים simanim are not דאורייתא deoraisa because you can't use them to
testify that the woman's husband died. That's what the ברייתא beraisa teaches
and that's a real legal point. To which we said, you know
what? Maybe if they were good סימנים simanim you could use it,
but we're talking about scenarios where they're like very generic סימנים. simanim.
Again, not at all what the ברייתא beraisa sounds like, but that's
maybe how we could explain why in that ברייתא beraisa the סימנים
simanim do not work to testify that the husband is dead. So
now the גמרא Gemara continues. אלא הא דתניא, Ela ha detanya, that
which we taught in the ברייתא, beraisa, מצאו קשור בכיסו בארנקי ובטבעת
או שמצאו בין כליו אפילו זמן מרובה כשר, matzo kashur bekiso be'arnakei
uvetaba'as o shematzo bein keilav afilu zman merubeh kasher, so that if,
you know, the it was found that the שליח shaliach who is
bringing a גט, get, you know, found that there was a גט
get that was, he lost the גט get and then he refound
it again where he had this before and he saw that it
was tied into, you know, it was it was tied it was
bound up with his wallet or with his ring or some type
of a personal item that the גט get was tied to and,
you know, the גט get that he lost and then he finds
it, so he could say, oh, I recognize the ring and the
wallet, obviously this is the גט get I lost. So once again
we're back to using סימנים simanim to actually for a personal status
issue, which would prove that סימנים דאורייתא. simanim deoraisa. Okay, מצאו קשור
בכיס, matzo kashur bekis, tied up into a wallet, you know. a
pouch or בארנקי be'arnaki or a wallet, ובטבעת ubetaba'at or a ring,
או שמצאו בין כליו o shematzo bein kelav or you found it
like amongst your personal items in your house. In all those cases,
אפילו זמן מרובה כשר, afilu zman merubeh kasher, even if you had
lost it for a while, that is evidence that this is the
גט get you have lost because it is with things that you
can recognize as yours. So now the גמרא gemara says, so that
doesn't necessarily prove, excuse me, I jumped ahead, that doesn't necessarily prove
that סימנים דאורייתא. simanim d'oraisa. That could be that you actually have
real direct recognition of those objects. It's not just סימנים. simanim. You
know that that's your wallet. You know that those are your garments.
But the גמרא gemara is now going through the question, back to
the question about: are we concerned that you might have lent out
your personal items? And that's what we're trying to prove or disprove.
So the גמרא gemara says like this: ואי סלקא דעתך חיישינן לשאלה,
ve'i salka dachach hayishinan l'she'ela,
if you say that in general we're concerned that people might have
lent out their personal items, which was the question raised before, so
if that's true, כי מצאו קשור בכיס מאי כשר? ki matzo kashur
bekis mai kasher? Just because it was bound up in your pouch,
why is that כשר? kasher? ניחוש לשאלה. neichosh l'she'ela.
So let's be concerned that maybe
it's a different גט get and you had lent somebody your pouch.
You had lent somebody your wallet. Now again, the likelihood that (a)
you lent them your wallet and (b) you lost a גט get
which had these names and this גט get has the same names
and the only question is: is it the same גט? get? You
know, when you sort of combine those factors, that seems to be
very strong evidence. But okay, the גמרא gemara isn't going down that
route. And the גמרא gemara is saying is: if you're concerned that
you lent out your personal items, why is this good evidence that
it's the same גט? get? So the גמרא gemara says: אמרינו, amrinu,
you can say, כיס וארנקי וטבעת לא מושיל אינשי. kis ve'arnaki vetaba'at
lo moshil inshi. People don't lend out, the same way you don't
lend out your donkey saddle, you don't lend out your pouch and
your wallet and your signet ring. כיס וארנקי משום דמסימני. kis ve'arnaki
mishum demasamni.
Your pouch and your wallet because that could be used just to
sort of do voodoo or magic against you. That's sort of what
רש״י Rashi says. מנחשי סימנא דאדם... menachshi simana d'adam... excuse me, רש״י
Rashi says something else, שמנחש כיסו שמוחל למזל, shemenachesh kiso shemochel lemazal,
that
it's a bad sign if you lend out your wallet or your
pouch. That sort of says like you're squandering your luck or something.
So that's bad luck to do that. וטבעת משום דמזייף. vetaba'at mishum
demezayef.
And your signet ring you don't lend out because that could be
used to forge your signature. Because that's what a signet ring does.
It would say that this was a document that you had signed
off on. Okay, so what we have said was is the evidence
of that you don't marry somebody off based on testifying on their
clothes led us into a question of: does it prove סימנים simanim
is not דאורייתא d'oraisa or does it prove we're concerned about lending
out your garments and lending out your effects? And if we do
say that we're generally concerned about lending out your effects, how come
it works here by the case of גט? get? To which the
answer is: those are the types of things that you would not
lend out. All right, כתנאי, ketannai, says the גמרא. gemara. Let's say
that this question of סימנים דאורייתא simanim d'oraisa is based on a
debate of תנאים. tannaim. אין מעידין על השומה. ein me'idin al hashuma.
With again, testifying that this is somebody's dead husband to allow the
woman to remarry, you don't testify on some type of
a swelling of the limbs, discoloration of the limbs. That's not enough
to say, oh yes, I know that he had a swollen thigh
and this guy had a swollen thigh and therefore it must be
the same husband, the same man. ואלעזר בן מהבאי אומר מעידין על
השומה. v'Elazar ben Mahabai omer me'idin al hashuma. No,
that is good enough to identify who the man is. So here
again we're dealing with a case of personal status. So it's a
question of what counts דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So isn't it reasonable to say
that this is a type of thing which is an average סימן,
siman, and they're debating whether an average סימן siman works at a
דאורייתא d'oraisa level? So the גמרא gemara says: מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי?
mai lav beha kamiflagi? Should we not say that this is the
debate? דתנא קמא סבר סימנים דרבנן. detanna kamma savar simanim derabbanan. The
תנא קמא tanna kamma says that סימנים simanim only work, of a
middle type of סימן, siman, only work at a דרבנן derabbanan level
and therefore this does not work for personal status. ואלעזר בן מהבאי
סבר סימנים דאורייתא. v'Elazar ben Mahabai savar simanim d'oraisa. No, it works
at a דאורייתא d'oraisa level and it does work.
Okay,
so that's one possible read. But the גמרא gemara says no, it's
not the only read. אמר רבא. amar Rava. So רבא Rava says
not necessarily. דכולי עלמא סימנים דאורייתא. dekoulei alma simanim d'oraisa. Everybody could
say that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא. d'oraisa. And the question here is
whether it falls into the category of a reasonable סימן. siman. והכא
בשומה מצויה בבני גילו קמיפלגי. vehacha beshuma metzuya bevnei gilo kamiflagi.
Are people of this person's age or מזל mazal or whatever it
is, you know, do other people... is this
a prevalent enough type of a bodily characteristic for a certain genre
of person? And if so, it doesn't even fall into a reasonable
סימן siman category. That's the debate. מר סבר שומה מצויה בבני גילו.
mar savar shuma metzuya bevnei gilo. One holds that
other people of this person's type will also have this type of
appearance. appearance, and therefore it's not even a reasonable סימן siman of
any sort. ואלעזר בן דבאי אומר V'Elazar ben Dovai omer and Elazar
ben Dovai would say מר סבר Mar savar excuse me שכיחא בבני
גילו shechicha b'vnei gilo מר סבר שאינה בבני גילו Mar savar she'eina
b'vnei gilo no
it's rare enough that it is in the normal category of a
reasonable good סימן. siman. That's one other way of reading it. Everybody
agrees that a middle level סימן siman is good and the question
is does this qualify as a middle level סימן? siman? איבעית אימא
Iba'it eima if you want you could say דכולי עלמא שומה אינה
בבני גילו. d'kulei alma shuma eina b'vnei gilo.
Everybody agrees that this is not a common סימן siman and this
and this is a reasonable middle level סימן. siman. So what's the
debate? והכא בסימנים עשויין להשתנות לאחר מיתה קמיפלגי. V'hacha b'simanim asuyin l'hishtanot
l'achar mita kamiflegi.
The question would be the guy died so is the fact that
one of the limbs is swollen
maybe that's not the way he looked when he died maybe that
was some type of change that happened after death. So everybody could
agree
סימנים דאורייתא simanim d'Oraita and this type of an appearance would normally
be in this middle סימן siman category. So why should it not
work? Because maybe something changed after he died. מר סבר סימנים עשויין
להשתנות לאחר מיתה Mar savar simanim asuyin l'hishtanot l'achar mita the חכמים
Chachamim say we're concerned that these types of something like this might
have changed after death so it is no longer a good סימן.
siman. ומר סבר U'mar savar and Elazar ben Dovai holds סימנים אינן
עשויין להשתנות לאחר מיתה simanim einan asuyin l'hishtanot l'achar mita that we're
not concerned that it changed and therefore it retains its status as
an average סימן. siman. איבעית אימא Iba'it eima and if you want
you could say דכולי עלמא שומה אינה עשויה להשתנות לאחר מיתה. d'kulei
alma shuma eina asuya l'hishtanot l'achar mita. Everybody would agree we're not
concerned about a change. וסימנים דרבנן. V'simanim d'Rabbanan.
Everybody would agree that סימנים simanim is only Rabbinic. So if we're
not concerned that it changed and it's only Rabbinic why would Elazar
ben Dovai say that you can rely on it to let the
woman marry? והכא בשומה סימן מובהק קמיפלגי. V'hacha b'shuma siman muvhak kamiflegi.
The question is the opposite of what we were saying before. Maybe
this שומה shuma this configuration of the body maybe it's not just
an average סימן siman maybe it's an expert סימן. siman. Maybe it's
a highly identifying mark and that's what Elazar ben Dovai holds. So
that's always the question: are people debating the standard or are they
debating whether something fits the standard or not? Are they debating whether
סימנים דאורייתא simanim d'Oraita or דרבנן? d'Rabbanan? Or maybe they all agree
that סימנים דרבנן simanim d'Rabbanan but they're debating does this fit into
the category of being an expert
סימן? siman? Or the opposite. Everybody agrees that סימנים דאורייתא simanim d'Oraita
but they're debating if this falls into the category of being like
a below average סימן. siman. So we could debate in which category
it fits into and not necessarily what the general הלכה halacha is
for the categories. Okay so that's another way of explaining it. אינה
עשויה להשתנות לאחר מיתה וסימנים דרבנן והכא בשומה סימן מובהק קמיפלגי Eina
asuya l'hishtanot l'achar mita v'simanim d'Rabbanan v'hacha b'shuma siman muvhak kamiflegi מר
סבר שומה סימן מובהק Mar savar shuma siman muvhak Elazar ben Dovai
holds that normal סימנים simanim is דרבנן d'Rabbanan but this שומה shuma
is the highest quality סימן siman an expertly identifying mark and that's
why it works as that everybody would agree is דאורייתא d'Oraita הוא
hu ומר סבר שומה לאו סימן מובהק הוא U'mar savar shuma lav
siman muvhak hu no it's an average סימן siman and average סימנים
simanim are דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. Okay
so we have many ways to explain the debate and at the
end we still don't know: we do know that there are these
three categories: not even a סימן siman average סימן siman סימן מובהק
siman muvhak and the question still is in the average סימן siman
category is that דאורייתא d'Oraita or דרבנן. d'Rabbanan. Let's do a little
more.
אמר רבא Amar Rava says Rava אם תמצי לומר סימנים לאו דאורייתא
Im timtzi lomar simanim lav d'Oraita if you were to say that
סימנים simanim are not דאורייתא d'Oraita so okay so then it wouldn't
an average סימן siman wouldn't work for get but we're saying that
חז"ל Chazal would have made a תקנה takana to let it work
for אבידה aveida to be sufficient to return an אבידה aveida on
the basis of it. So he wants to understand what would have
motivated them to allow an אבידה aveida to be returned by a
סימן siman if the תורה Torah normally would have demanded עדים. edim.
היכי מהדרינן אבידתא בסימנים? Heichi mahrinan aveidata b'simanim?
On what basis did חז"ל Chazal find it appropriate to say that
we could return an אבידה aveida based on סימנים? simanim? So here's
the logic. It makes sense at a societal level. דניחא ליה למוציא
אבידה דנהדרה בסימנים היכי דכי אבדה ליה לדידיה נמי נהדרו ליה בסימנים
D'nicha lei l'motzi aveida d'nahadra b'simanim heichi d'chi avda lei l'didei nami
nahadru lei b'simanim
it's good for the guy who finds the אבידה aveida to return
it with סימנים simanim right because if we would say סימנים simanim
would not be
דאורייתא d'Oraita then and then people wouldn't return it with סימנים simanim
you would if you found אבידות aveidot it'd be more possible for
you to keep it because people would have less of a reason
to think they would be able to get it back if סימנים
simanim would not be the currency and the basis for which to
get it back. But nevertheless we say for people who find אבידות
aveidot they would want there to be this principle in place that
they should return it with סימנים simanim because ultimately they will be
able to be the beneficiaries of it when they lose things. And
to some degree that makes sense right because people are more thinking
about if I lose my thing I want to make sure to
get it back. rather than like oh if I find something I
want to be able to keep it. Okay so therefore people would
want to have this principle in place to more return objects and
more cases because of סימנים simanim so then even if they find
it because then they will be assured that they'll get their object
back if they lose their object. So that seems very reasonable but
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this אמר ליה רב ספרא לרבא Amar lei Rav Safra le-Rava
so רב ספרא Rav Safra said back to רבא Rava וכי אדם
עושה טובה לעצמו בממון שאינו שלו Ve-chi adam oseh tovah le-atzmo be-mamon
she-eino shelo?
How can somebody be benefiting themselves with money which is not theirs?
Means what? Here I'm the guy that found the אבידה. avedah. Now
this אבידה avedah maybe I should not return it to ראובן Reuven
because ראובן Reuven only gave me סימנים simanim and really I should
only return it to שמעון Shimon you know because שמעון Shimon will
bring along עדים. edim. But I'm saying you know oh but I'll
want to return it to ראובן Reuven so that if I lose
something it'll get back to me. How can I go ahead and
benefit myself, have a policy in place that will benefit me if
I lose an אבידה avedah by giving this to ראובן Reuven when
it should be there should be going to שמעון? Shimon?
I'm using שמעון'ס Shimon's money, something that might be שמעון'ס Shimon's property
and I'm giving it to ראובן Reuven so I'll benefit when I
lose an object. That doesn't make sense why we would sort of
care about that calculus. You're not in a position to make that
type of a trade-off. So it's going to be basically the same
idea but just framed from the other perspective. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this אלא ניחא ליה לבעל אבידה. Ella nicha lei le-ba'al
avedah.
So רב פפא Rav Papa says again אלא ניחא ליה לבעל אבידה
למייהב סימנים. ella nicha lei le-ba'al avedah le-meiav simanim.
So you have to look at it from the perspective of the
person who lost the אבידה. avedah. Because from that person's perspective, right,
to allow it to get returned by סימנים simanim they are the
ones that are potentially losing out.
So that and it's their אבידה avedah and their אבידה avedah might
now go to a wrong person if you return it by סימנים
simanim and you would actually normally need עדים. edim. So if we're
going to justify the תקנה takkanah we have to explain how it
works from their perspective. Okay אלא ניחא ליה ella nicha lei let's
see that again אלא ניחא ליה לבעל אבידה למייהב סימנים. ella nicha
lei le-ba'al avedah le-meiav simanim. It is in their interest that the
principle should be around that you return an אבידה avedah with סימנים
simanim even if somebody the wrong person might get their אבידה. avedah.
Why? ולמשקליה U-lemishklei that you give the סימנים simanim and you take
it. מדידע Mi-de-yada because you realize if you if you might be
that person that loses the object דעדים לית ליה de-edim leis lei
that you won't necessarily have witnesses that can testify that they recognize
that this is your object ומימר כל עמא לא ידעי סימנים מובהקים
דידי. u-mei-amar kulei alma lo yadi simanim muvhakim didi.
Look not everybody knows the same סימנים simanim that I know. You
know maybe somebody will be able to give סימנים simanim but I'll
have better סימנים. simanim. I mean I'm the owner and we'll see
later that you know if it's a if I give you know
better סימן siman if somebody gives סימנים simanim but my סימנים simanim
are more accurate or more evidence that I'm that I really know
the object I'm going to win out and I'll get it. So
it's in my interest as the owner if you demanded that I
always produce עדים edim there's going to be a lot of objects
I'm going to lose that I'm not going to get back. But
if you institute the principle that I can get it back with
סימנים simanim okay there's a small risk that somebody will get it
who doesn't deserve it. But since it's my object I will feel
confident that it'll be most likely much more likely that I will
get that back and that would be in my best interest to
work with a סימנים simanim principle rather than an עדים edim principle.
And I can always have better סימנים simanim than the next guy.
Okay so כל עמא לא ידעי סימנים מובהקים דידי. kulei alma lo
yadi simanim muvhakim didi. Not everybody knows the really expert סימנים simanim
of this object.
ואנא יהיבנא סימנים מובהקים דידי Va-ana yahivna simanim muvhakim didi I'll give
the expert סימנים simanim ושקלינא ליה u-shaklina lei and I'll take it.
Okay so that's why and that's if you're going to institute a
principle that's going to change things around you have to think about
who are the parties that are going to lose out. So the
potential parties to lose out are the people who lost their objects
and now it might go to a wrong person. But we can
explain that the תקנה takkanah makes sense because ultimately it is in
their best interest for the people who lose it to use the
principle of סימנים. simanim. Now the phrase of סימנים מובהקים simanim muvhakim
is a little distracting or like imprecise because even if סימנים simanim
were דרבנן de-rabbanan as we've been saying before סימנים מובהקים simanim muvhakim
are דאורייתא. de-oraisa. So you have to understand it's being used a
little bit more loosely. Okay so so I as the person who
lose people lose objects might not have עדים edim you know in
a lot of cases they won't have עדים. edim. In a lot
of cases they won't have super great סימנים simanim but they will
often in the large majority of cases have סימנים simanim and have
סימנים simanim that will be better than somebody else's guesswork. So ultimately
it is in their best interest that סימנים simanim be an option
of getting back your אבידה avedah and not just עדים. edim. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this okay but if we're
always going to be thinking about it from their perspective. Perspective, there'll
be there's going to be one type of a case that it's
never in their interest to expand the ways in which the thing
can go back. What's that case? A שטר חוב. shtar chov. Let's
take a look. אלא הא דתנן, Ella ha detnan, that which we
taught in a משנה, mishna, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, אחד הלווה משלושה יחזיר ללווה, Echad haloveh mishlosha yachzir
laloveh, שלושה שלווה מן האחד יחזיר למלווה. Shlosha shelava min ha'echad yachzir
lamilveh.
You find three documents. So if the three documents had that
Reuven borrowed from Shimon and the second document was Reuven borrowed from
Levi and the third document was Reuven borrowed from Yehuda, then the
common denominator is Reuven as the borrower, so you assume that they
all fell from Reuven. That Reuven had borrowed money from three people
and he paid up the debts and he was carrying and he
got these documents back and therefore he dropped them all. That's why
they all have Reuven's name as the borrower on it. If it's
the reverse, if Reuven borrowed from Shimon and Levi
borrowed from Shimon and Yehuda borrowed from Shimon, and you have three
of those three documents that have that say that respectively, then since
the borrower is the common denominator, you assume that these were all
being held by the borrower and Shimon was the one that was
holding on to all these documents. Alright, so that's the teaching of
the משנה mishna and now let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So that makes sense, but the גמרא Gemara asks the following question.
ניחא ליה ללווה לאהדורי ליה למלווה? Nicha leh laloveh le'ahadore leh lamilveh?
Why would the לווה loveh ever want to be the ability to
use סימנים? simanim? It's in the לווה's loveh interest that when you
find a שטר חוב שטר חוב, shtar chov shtar chov, an IOU
document, that you make it as hard as possible to return that
because, you
know, if for him, for the לווה, loveh, right, if he's holding
on to it, it means it's been paid. If you don't return
it to the לווה loveh or the מלווה, malveh, the מלווה malveh
can't use it. The only way this document, this IOU can be
used against him is if it's returned to the מלווה. malveh. So
it's always in the לווה's loveh best interest that you make a
שטר חוב שטר חוב, shtar chov shtar chov, an IOU, as difficult
to return if it gets found as possible. So why would we
ever return a שטר חוב shtar chov based on סימנים? simanim? There
are some people who lose שטרי חוב שטרי חוב, shtarei chov shtarei
chov, לווים loves who would never want us to employ this principle.
Okay, so why would we ever do it? So the גמרא Gemara
says the following. The גמרא Gemara says, אמר
ליה התם סברה הוא. Amar leh hatam sevara hu. No, there, whether
it's the לווה loveh likes it or doesn't like it, you don't
need the רבנן rabbanan תקנה. takana. There it's almost like a סימן
מובהק. siman muvhak. Okay, the logic is compelling who it fell from.
סברה הוא אחד הלווה משלושה יחזיר ללווה דגבי לווה שכיחי גבי מלווה
לא שכיחי. Sevara hu echad haloveh mishlosha yachzir laloveh degabi loveh shechichei
gabi milveh lo shechichei. Why would there be three documents that Reuven
borrowed from Shimon, Reuven borrowed from Levi, Reuven borrowed from Yehuda unless
they all came from Reuven? So obviously they came from the לווה.
loveh. שמע מינה מלווה נפלו, Shema mina miloveh naflu, they fell from
the לווה. loveh. שלושה שלווה מן האחד, Shlosha shelava min ha'echad, if
three people borrowed from one lender, Reuven borrowed from Shimon, Levi borrowed
from Shimon, Yehuda borrowed from Shimon, so the compelling evidence is that
they fell from Shimon. So יחזיר למלווה דגבי מלווה שכיחי דגבי לווה
לא שכיחי. yachzir lamilveh degabi milveh shechichei degabi loveh lo shechichei. To
have three documents of Shimon lending out money is something you would
find by Shimon, you wouldn't find it by the borrower. So what
does the answer mean? The גמרא Gemara is basically saying, that's like
a סימן מובהק. siman muvhak. We don't need a תקנה takana in
that case to return it to the מלווה. malveh. Okay, that's not
just a normal סימן. siman. If they all said that Shimon lent
to different people, then clearly they all fell from Shimon and so
that's effectively a סימן מובהק. siman muvhak. But the גמרא Gemara isn't
done. And now finally כח, kaf chet, which is actually technically what
today's דף daf is. אלא, Ella, says the גמרא. Gemara. הא דתנן,
Ha detnan, that which we taught in a משנה, mishna, מצא תכריך
של שטרות, matza tachrich shel shtarot, if you found like a bundle
of שטרות shtarot of IOUs, או אגודה של שטרות, o aguda shel
shtarot, like, you know, or like a, you know, or like them
tied up
together, one's like they're rolled together, tied together, הרי זה יחזיר, harei
ze yachzir, you return it. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case?
Meaning you give it to the person who can identify, yeah, there
were three tied together with this type of a string. Who do
you give it back to? The לווה loveh or the מלווה? malveh?
Right, so it depends who's giving the סימנים. simanim. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. What's the case? So
הכי נמי דניחא ליה ללווה לאהדורי ליה למלווה? Hachi nami denicha leh
laloveh le'ahadore leh lamilveh? So there clearly you're giving it back to
the person who's able to give the סימנים simanim and say, yeah,
there were three שטרות, shtarot, they were tied with a red string.
So that's a clear case where you will return it to the
מלווה malveh with סימנים. simanim. So the גמרא's Gemara question is now
a good one. That's a normal case of returning something with a
סימן. siman. Why would we ever allow an IOU document to be
returned by a סימן? siman? The לווה loveh would never want to
expand the opportunities in which an IOU document could be returned, so
it is never working according to his interest. So how can we
say this is in everybody's best interest? All right, so that's a
good question. Now we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says in a
minute, but we should pause to realize that there are two responses
here. One response which תוספות Tosfos raises is, well, now I'm a
לוה, loveh, but maybe next month I'll be a מלוה. malveh. So
maybe it is in my best interest that we use that because
sometimes I'll borrow and sometimes I'll lend. So תוספות's Tosfos answer to
that is like, okay, but right now it's not in your interest.
There's probably a better answer. תוספות Tosfos was living at a time
when things were more commercial, so people could be borrowers sometimes and
lenders at other times. At an earlier stage, the wealthy people were
always the lenders and the poor people were always the borrowers. So
just so somebody who is going to find themselves in always a
situation of borrowing and never a situation of lending, it would never
be in their interest to expand the opportunities of returning a שטר
חוב. Shtar Chov. That's one question. Do we look at it big
picture or maybe big picture doesn't even matter in a certain type
of a society? But the other point is, even if it's true
that it will never be in the לוה's loveh interest to return
it, if we're going to institute a general principle that you return
with סימנים, simanim, are we going to really like micro-decide of every
little subcategory if it makes sense? No, broadly speaking, societally it makes
sense to return things with סימנים, simanim, even if in a particular
genre of like IOU documents, half of the people won't want us
to do it. Now that's what at least I would say. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
אמר רבא סימנים דאורייתא. Ella amar Rava simanim de-Oraisa. So רבא Rava
says, you know what? I'm convinced by that. The fact that we
return a שטר חוב Shtar Chov with סימנים, simanim, even though it
would never be in the interest of the לוה, loveh, proves to
me that the principle of סימנים simanim must be a דאורייתא de-Oraisa
principle, because חז"ל Chazal would not have been מתקן metaken it in
a way in which it would not benefit all the relevant parties.
And what's the פסוק? pasuk? דכתיב והיה עמך דרוש אחיך אותו. De-ksiv
vehaya imcha derosh achicha oso.
Interesting,
he doesn't quote our משנה Mishna which was שמלה, simla, the garment.
He quotes the other פסוק, pasuk, it's with you until your friend
seeks it out. הכי תעלה על דעתך שינתנו קודם שידרשנו? Hachi ta'aleh
al da'atach she-yitnu kodem she-yidreshenu? Would you think you return it before
he seeks it out? אלא דרשהו אם רמאי הוא אם אינו רמאי,
Ella darshehu im ramai hu im eino ramai, but you have to
figure out if he's deceiving or not deceiving. And he says, לאו
בסימנים? lav be-simanim? It must be with סימנים. simanim. שמע מינה. shema
mina. That's a good proof. Which is pretty funny because, A, as
the גמרא Gemara said before, no, maybe we could determine if he's
a רמאי ramai or not with עדים, edim, right? And he abandoned
the actual פסוק pasuk used in the משנה Mishna itself that said
סימנים. simanim. And the case that's pushing him there, the שטר חוב
Shtar Chov case, at least in my mind and we'll see in
a minute, is also is not the biggest evidence. But רבא Rava
would likes to think that it is דאורייתא de-Oraisa based on that
argument and would like to hinge it on the פסוק pasuk of
דרוש אחיך אותו. derosh achicha oso. Let's just do a little bit
more.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, אם תמצא לומר סימנים דאורייתא,
im timtza lomar simanim de-Oraisa, if we were to think that סימנים
simanim would be דאורייתא... de-Oraisa... so before he can finish his sentence,
the גמרא Gemara interrupts him. אם תמצא לומר? Im timtza lomar? If
you would think to say? פשיטא ליה סימנים דאורייתא. Pashit leh simanim
de-Oraisa. It's just a second ago you said that you concluded that
סימנים simanim are דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. No, משום דאיכא למימר כדי שניתן סימנים
כדי שניתן. mishum de-ika le-meimar kedei she-nisan simanim kedei she-nisan. No,
because just because of the פסוק pasuk of דרוש אחיך אותו, derosh
achicha oso, that doesn't prove it. Maybe that's talking with עדים, edim,
maybe it's not talking with סימנים. simanim. Okay, so in the end
I concede, even though I wanted to conclude סימנים דאורייתא, simanim de-Oraisa,
I can concede that I haven't really proved it. But let's now
work with that assumption that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא. de-Oraisa. Even assuming
סימנים simanim are דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, there still is a hierarchy if two
different people are making different competing claims.
Okay? So סימנים וסימנים יניח. simanim ve-simanim yaniach. If you have one,
ראובן Reuven is giving סימנים simanim and שמעון Shimon is giving equivalent
weight סימנים, simanim, so they neutralize one another. You don't give it
to either person. You hold onto it until it could be clarified
further or you just hold onto it for forever.
סימנים ועדים, Simanim ve-edim, even if סימנים simanim is דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, עדים
edim are better. So if I go ahead and I say it
was a blue and white striped umbrella and then other people come
and they testify that they know, they see this umbrella and they
recognize it not as my umbrella but as שמעון's Shimon umbrella, that
will beat out my
סימנים. simanim. Okay. So סימנים ועדים יינתן לבעל העדים, simanim ve-edim yinasen
le-ba'al ha-edim, give it to the one who has the witnesses. סימנים
וסימנים ועד אחד. Simanim ve-simanim ve-ed echad. Now let's say I say
it's a blue and white umbrella and somebody else said it was
a blue and white umbrella, not in front of one another, but
this guy had one עד ed that said I recognize it as
שמעון's Shimon as שמעון's Shimon umbrella. So maybe you would think oh
that one עד ed tips the scale. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, עד אחד כמאן דליתא דמי. ed echad ke-man de-leisa dami. One
witness has no value, which is interesting because sometimes one witness plays
a role in ממונות mamonos to make a שבועה, shvua, but maybe
it that's for a שבועה, shvua, but in this type of a
thing it has no value and it doesn't tip the scales. ויניח,
Veyaniach, and in that case it's just... were totally equivalent and you
do not return it to either person. Okay, וינח. v'yanich. עדי אריגה
ועדי נפילה. edei ariga v'edei nefila.
Let's say I have witnesses that say I wove the garment and
somebody else have witnesses that say that Shimon dropped the garment. So
in that case, תינתן לעדי נפילה, tinasein l'edei nefila, you give it
back to Shimon. Why? דאמרינן, d'amrinan, because you say, זבוני זבניה ומיניה
דאחרינא נפל, zivuni zavneh u'minei d'achrina nefal, yes,
I wove it, but that didn't mean that I was the most
recent owner. I could have, you know, woven it and then sold
it to Shimon. So if there's עדים eidim that he was the
one from whom it fell, then that beats out my עדים eidim
that I was the one who wove it, who made it. Okay,
now, מידת ארכו ומידת רחבו. midas arko u'midas rachvo. Let's say I'm
testifying to the width of the garment and Shimon is testifying to
the length of the garment, you know, let's say it's a cloak
or something.
So, תינתן למידת ארכו. tinasein l'midas arko. So being able to testify
to the length of it is more of an indicator that they're
the real owner. Why? דמידת רחבו שוערא כמה שייר לה כד מכסי
לה מרה.
d'midas rachvo shiurei kama
shayer la kad mikasei la mareh.
Because I could estimate the width when I'm looking at somebody wearing
it. I'm looking at somebody wearing it, I'm saying oh, that's a
medium, that's a large, he's like a 36 waist or something like
that. And then I hear that he lost his garment so I
can say, oh, I know it was a 36 waist. But the
height is something that if I'm not the owner, I would less
be in a position to have a good guess about it. Now
I don't know, you know, some people are better at estimating people's
heights than people's waist or whatever, so I'm not exactly sure what
type of garment we're talking about, but whatever it is, it means
that who do we think might have seen it and not owned
it and who's more likely to have owned it? So if one
is giving one dimension and the other the other, and one indicates
more something that you would only know if you were really the
owner, it would be harder for you to know if you weren't
the owner, then that's the one that will win out. Okay? So
that's that. תינתן למידת ארכו דמידת רחבו שוערא, tinasein l'midas arko d'midas
rachvo shiurei, okay, וכד מכסי לה מרה וקאי v'kad mikasei la mareh
v'kai when the owner was wearing it and standing. Okay, ומידת ארכו
לא משתערא ליה u'midas arko lo mishtaara leih
and it's harder to estimate the length of the garment if you're
not the owner. Now, מידת ארכו ומידת רחבו ומידת גמיו, midas arko
u'midas rachvo u'midas gamav,
one person gives the length and the width and the other person
gives the area, like the total, like the, you know, like when
you have to measure luggage for, like,
for the airplanes, you know, you add the width and the length
and the depth. So one person gives the combination width and length
and the other person gives no, the width was, you know, 10
inches and the length was whatever, 6 feet, whatever it might be.
So obviously the one that gives them separate is more precise. So
in that case, גמיו gamav means like a gamma, like it's a,
you know, like a, like it's an L, whatever, like it's a
width and a length combined. So תינתן למידת ארכו ורחבו. tinasein l'midas
arko v'rachvo. You give it to the one that gave the, that
gave them broken down into width and length. מידת ארכו ומידת רחבו
ומידת משקלותיו. midas arko u'midas rachvo u'midas mishkelosav.
So one person gives the length, one the width, and one gives
the weight. תינתן למידת משקלותיו. tinasein l'midas mishkelosav.
Okay, you give it to the guy who gives the weight, because
it's much easier to guess at the height and width of a
garment than it is to guess at its weight. Now, הוא אומר
סימני הגט והיא אומרת סימני הגט. hu omer simanei haget v'hi omeres
simanei haget.
Let's say we're back to the גט get case. If we think
סימנים דאורייתא, simanim d'oraisa, you return a גט get to the woman.
But here's the thing, the husband owned it and then afterwards if
it was given to the wife, then the wife owned it. So
you would return it to the wife because since she only owns
it once she receives it, she wouldn't know the סימנים simanim if
she had never received it. So therefore if she gives סימנים, simanim,
if he gives סימנים simanim and he gives סימנים, simanim, you give
it to her. How would she know the סימנים simanim if she
hadn't received it? Obviously he knows the סימנים, simanim, it started with
him. Okay, so let's take a look.
הוא אומר סימני הגט והיא אומרת סימני הגט, תינתן לה. hu omer
simanei haget v'hi omeres simanei haget, tinasein lah. You give it to
her. Okay, because as I just said, how would she know it
if she had never received it? So the גמרא Gemara says במאי,
bemai, what's the case? אילימא במידת ארכו ורחבו, eilima be'midas arko v'rachvo,
so if it's something like the length and the width of the
גט, get, so דילמא בהדי דנקיט ליה חזיתיה. dilma bahadei d'nakit leih
chazisyei. How do you know she received it? I mean, obviously he
wrote it, right? It started with him. But maybe she saw him
holding onto it and that's something that you could look and approximate
and guess. So why does that prove that she received it? So
אלא, ela, so that would not be enough to assume that she
received it. אלא נקב יש לו בצד אות פלונית. ela nekev yesh
lo b'tzad os plonis. It would be that she said, no, in
the fifth line in the letter ב beis there was a hole.
Something that she would only know if she had actually received it.
Fine. הוא אומר סימני החוט והיא אומרת סימני החוט. hu omer simanei
hachut v'hi omeres simanei hachut.
Now let's say there was a string that, you know, that tied
the גט get together. And they both describe it, it was a
red string and she says it was a red string. So ינתן
לה, Yinaten lah, again give it to her because how else would
she know if she hadn't received it? But now it's going to
be the same question: במה, Bameh, what's the case? אילימא בחוורא ובסומקא,
Ilima bechivra ubesumka, it was a white string or a red string,
ודילמא בתר דנקט לה חזיתיה. Vedilma batar denakat lah chaziteih. Maybe she
saw it after he was holding it. Maybe she never received it.
She just saw that it was tied with a white or a
red string. אלא במידת ארכא? Ella bemidat arka? No, but she said
it was a string that was six inches long. Now again, that
is also something that maybe you can estimate, but the גמרא Gemara
is at least here assuming that probably she wouldn't be able, she
wouldn't have gotten it right if she had not actually received it.
Last case: הוא אומר בחפיסה והיא אומרת בחפיסה. Hu omer bechafisa vehi
omeret bechafisa. You know, he says the גט get was stored in
my, you know, in my carrying case and she says it was
stored in his carrying case. So in that case ינתן לו, Yinaten
lo, you give it to him, not to her. מאי טעמא? Mai
taama? Why? מידע ידעה דכל מדאית ליה בחפיסה הוא דמנח ליה Meda
yadaa dechol midait leh bechafisa hu demanach leh
because she doesn't even have to have seen it. She just knows
her husband's habits and she knows that anything that he has, anything
precious, any important, you know, document he keeps in his carrying case.
So that doesn't prove at all that she received it. Okay, so
we will end with this and the whole discussion of סימנים דאורייתא
או דרבנן, simanim de-Oraita o de-Rabbanan, different levels of סימנים, simanim, מובהק,
muvhak, לא מובהק, lo muvhak, average, even below average, and then the
big נפקא מינה nafka mina would be, well if it's דרבנן de-Rabbanan
we have to explain why it was in, you know, the best
interest of the people that lose their objects to have this institution
in place. But the biggest נפקא מינה nafka mina is if it's
דאורייתא, de-Oraita, then it applies even by personal status, even by גט,
get, and even if it's דאורייתא, de-Oraita, there are hierarchies competing against
עדים edim or different types of סימנים, simanim, which ones do we
think are the bigger evidence of who actually owns it? Good, we
will end here.